-[Sitara cries]
-[SHIRA] Hey! Listen!
You want to get that book back,
don't you?
[Sitara gasps softly]
Huh?
[♪ opening theme song playing]
[battle cry]
[SITARA (ADULT)]
The thirteenth century
saw the rise of a vast empire
that swept across Eurasia.
Genghis Khan,
the "universal ruler."
He was hailed as the Great Khan,
as he and his kin
built the Mongol Empire.
Although the Mongols were
originally a small,
nomadic tribe,
by the year 1206,
they had conquered
the other steppe tribes
and become a major power.
A short time later, they began
advancing even further.
Foraying into
the various nations
that bordered the steppes.
Greetings, my brothers.
[ALL] Tolui.
[slurps]
Haven't you drunk enough?
Welcome back.
[Tolui laughs]
How was the Khwarazm campaign?
It went well, except,
we lost quite a few soldiers.
The shame is mine.
Your indecision is to blame.
You simply had to follow
Father's orders, Jochi.
[ÖGEDEI] That's enough, you two.
What about you, Tolui?
You were in Persia, right?
Indeed. I brought honor to
Genghis Khan's name in battle.
[laughs]
Fitting for the Otchigin.
Our future emperor.
[TOLUI] Not to mention,
I acquired something good.
A foreign book, huh?
I am told it's called Elements.
♪
[TOLUI] Before leaving home,
my wife asked me for this book
as a token
of my conquests.
What a modest woman!
After all,
she could have asked me
to bring back gold
or rare jewels instead.
She's so very special to me.
I'd do anything just
to make her smile.
[Ögedei whistles]
So what's written
on these pages?
[TOLUI] Hm?
I have no clue.
[ALL] Uh...
Oh, so you have a scholar
who can explain its contents?
[TOLUI] No.
Can your wife read tomes
that are written
in foreign tongues?
[TOLUI] Not that I know of.
[laughs]
[ÖGEDEI] Oh, dear.
[SHIRA] See,
I'm planning on introducing you
to Prince Tolui
as soon as possible.
You're a scholar's daughter,
aren't you?
I would've preferred
to volunteer myself,
but I can only read
and write a few simple things.
I do pick up
new languages quickly, though.
[SITARA] Why did she even
want that book, anyway?
[SHIRA] Hm?
-Uh, I don't know.
-She can't read the words.
[SHIRA] And she asked for it
instead of gold or silver.
Strange, to be sure.
Still, this is your chance
to serve the imperial family.
And to have that book back
in your hands again.
Doesn't sound
like too bad a deal,
wouldn't you say? [gasps]
[SITARA] The Mongol emperor?
Serve his family?
No. That aside, worse still.
[TOLUI] Before leaving home,
my wife asked me for this book.
[SITARA] My mistress died
over such a trifle?
So, um, what happened was
most unfortunate.
And I do regret it.
But I didn't have a choice.
I'm doing everything I can
to try and get
in their good favor.
I don't ever want to be sent
to the front lines.
Boys who are around my age
end up at the very front
of their expedition armies...
as human shields.
-[Sitara exhales]
-[battle cry]
I see.
You're too young
to grow a beard,
yet they took you?
Yes, that's right.
-No, enough talk of the past!
-[gasps softly]
This is my big chance
to move up in the world.
For the first time,
a path to success based on merit
has opened up to us.
I will do whatever it takes
to thrive and succeed.
Now you can finally
make the most of your education.
Well, that and your
fetching face.
If all the stars become aligned,
one day, you could become
an attendant
to a high-ranking figure.
Mm?
Her smile is quite fetching,
as you can see!
[SHIRA] That's the very reason
you ought to do something.
But what exactly?
How could I possibly know
what course of action
I'm supposed to take here?
What should I do?
[MUHAMMAD]
But if one were to study
and become wise,
then one would know
the best course of action
to take,
no matter what the problem
might be.
That's always.
[Sitara breathes shakily]
[Sitara grunts]
[SHIRA] Uh?
♪
[Shira exhales softly]
[SITARA] I am well-versed
in ancient wisdom
and modern teachings alike.
Needless to say,
I am able to read
Euclid's Elements.
And you're right.
I want to lead a cushy life,
eating amazing food every day.
This is my chance!
If the both of us work together,
then we can make it happen!
Uh, yeah.
So, um, my name's Shira.
-Mm?
-And I'm from Samarkand.
My name's Sitara.
Sitara?
Hold on.
With a garish name like that...
Yes, I am a slave.
And what of it?
[Shira sighs]
[SHIRA]
We're in a new social order,
but being well-born
still gets you a long way.
Especially when dealing
with the imperial family.
Well, you can just lie.
Let's go with
a more dignified name.
[Sitara chuckles softly]
In that case...
[in English] Listen,
anybody who's granted
an audience with the Mongols
must pass between two fires.
'Cause they all believe
fire has the power
to purify evil.
[SITARA] A heathen ritual, huh?
[SHIRA] Also,
you must never step
on the entrance's threshold.
If you do,
you'll be put to death.
[in English]
"Greetings, scholar's daughter.
I am glad to see
you're still alive,
so says His Highness,"
he says.
[Sitara, in English]
My name is...
Fatima, Your Highness.
♪
[SITARA (ADULT)] These fires
won't ever erase them.
Not those tender days
that only exist
in my memories now.
Nor my ties to the mistress,
and the others.
If there's one thing I know
I can still do,
it's taking that book back.
Until that day, I shall remain
my mistress' slave.
[wind blows]
Well, I have avoided a fate
on the front lines,
thanks to the commander's
good word. Huh?
Is she Tolui's wife?
No. Princess Sorghaghtani
should be at the Mongols'
home camp right now,
so that definitely isn't her
over there.
I wonder
who she could be, then.
One of the generals' wives?
[SITARA] What?
The Mongols always bring
quite a few women with them,
even out
on military expeditions.
Women on an expedition?
I can't even begin
to imagine it.
First, I need to
learn about them.
Shira, teach me some
simple Mongolian words.
I want to know their language.
Sure. In return, I ask that
you help me in times of need.
Of course I will.
We're both on the same side,
aren't we?
Everybody here
is my sworn enemy.
As alone as I may be...
I'll fight to the bitter end.
[hoofbeats]
[ÖGEDEI]
So, there you are, Töregene.
It's Prince Ögedei.
[attendant gasps softly]
What? No words of appreciation
for your husband who's returned
from battle?
[TÖREGENE]
You are mistaken.
I am not your wife.
I am your enemy.
[SITARA (ADULT)]
The year is 1221.
The Mongol army has been resting
for a short time in Taloqan.
But now, they are setting out
once again in the autumn.
The army heads south
for the Khwarazmian Empire.
They intend to swiftly vanquish
the empire's last ruler.
The conflict
that ultimately follows
will go down in history
as the Battle of the Indus.
Less noticed by history,
is that those taken captive
in Persia
have continued their long march
to the Mongol home camp.
It's been half of a year.
How much longer
will this march take?
-[SOLDIER] Halt!
-[ALL] Hm?
[all sigh]
[SOLDIER] Begin constructing
the gers immediately!
An honored guest of the
Great Khan is heading here,
traveling all the way
from the east.
We are to set up camp
and provide him
with lodging for the night.
[cow moos]
[indistinct chatter]
-[SITARA] I help with this?
-[SOLDIER] Mm?
No, this is a job for a man.
Understand, yes.
There's still much about
the Mongols' way of life
that I find very puzzling.
But I think I'm slowly
starting to understand it.
♪
They're all totally helpless
without me around.
[SITARA] For example,
their tents are always built
so that their entrances
are oriented south.
Hey, you there! It's time
to water the livestock!
[SITARA] In addition to that,
they seem to follow
a rigorous daily schedule.
[sighs]
It makes me wonder
how they're able to keep track
of the time so accurately.
Uh?
I see, a sundial...
where the light falls
inside the house
tells them what time it is.
Hmm.
It's quite clever to have
the whole house act as a clock.
Uh?
Although, an astrolabe
would be able to tell the time
more precisely.
This is nothing
but the wisdom of savages.
[indistinct chatter]
Have you heard?
They say tonight's guest
is an Eastern sage
who knows the secret
to immortality.
Immortality?
-[CHIEFTAIN] Excuse me.
-[ALL] Mm?
Good evening, ladies.
We are Uyghurs
from the city close to here.
We come with an offering
for the master sage.
Do you think you could show us
where he is?
-Not me.
-I would be too scared.
But why?
[SITARA] The idea of an immortal
is rather creepy.
But still...
[SITARA]
Please follow this way.
Huh? Oh, is that you, Chieftain?
Oh-ho, Chinqai! I didn't realize
you were accompanying the sage.
My apologies. I should call you
Lord Chinqai, shouldn't I?
[laughs]
There's no need for that.
You helped me out greatly
when I was a mere peddler.
[CHIEFTAIN]
Gifts for the master sage.
Wine, bread, and watermelon
from our city of Janbaliq.
Oh, my! Watermelon!
-These look wonderful.
-[Sitara exclaims]
All right, go on ahead.
[Sitara exclaims]
[CHINQAI] Here.
You'll bring this in with them.
Oh, but I... I don't...
Go, now. Follow them.
But...
[breathes uneasily]
[SITARA] An immortal?
Can someone like that
really exist?
I'll have to go see the truth
for myself.
[chuckles softly]
Allow me to introduce you.
He was personally invited here
by the Great Khan
to share his wisdom,
and is currently in the midst
of a long journey to the west.
This is Master Changchun,
the highly respected sage.
[SITARA] How scary!
He looks like he's been alive
for over 200 years!
-The offering, if you will.
-[Sitara gasps]
[Changchun mumbles]
[INTERPRETER] Hm.
Mm-hmm.
Master Changchun asks you
the following...
"Did anyone here
see the solar eclipse
on the first day
of the fifth month?"
[Sitara gasps]
[CHIEFTAIN] The solar eclipse?
Oh, yes,
there certainly was one.
During the hour
of the snake.
About seven-tenths of the sun
must have been obscured.
-[SITARA] Mm... I, too.
-[ALL] Huh?
[SITARA] I saw eclipse.
On that day, travel passing
close to Samarkand.
When sun began to hide.
The sky grew slightly dark.
And the sun, maybe six
in ten parts became hidden.
[BOTH] Huh?
[SITARA] Crescent shadows
through the trees.
A solar eclipse.
Master Muhammad might've kept
a record of this.
But I don't even know
the exact time right now.
Mm? [gasps softly]
That time, light from sun...
shone onto poles of the roof.
I saw, in the tent.
Oh.
[CHINQAI] That would signal
the hour of the dragon.
Does that mean the eclipse
started later around here
than where you were?
When Master Changchun
witnessed the eclipse,
he was staying near
the Kherlen River
off to the east.
That was midday.
Even later, then.
[INTERPRETER] He was still able
to see the stars in the sky.
[CHIEFTAIN] Hm. So there are
different degrees of eclipsing?
[CHANGCHUN] Hmm.
[INTERPRETER]
"During a solar eclipse,
the moon casts its shadow
over the sun.
-One could liken it...
-[Sitara gasps]
...to obstructing this flame
with a fan."
-[Changchun mumbles]
-"From where I sit,
the flame is not visible,
but the rest of you see
a different picture."
The world is indeed
a truly wide place.
[cattle bleating]
[CHINQAI] I'm sorry.
I didn't realize that
you weren't part of their group.
-[SITARA] Huh?
-My name is Chinqai.
I'm a Uyghur as well.
Though I was able
to pick up a bit of Persian
back in my peddling days.
Oh, my name is Fatima.
It is nice to meet you.
I am traveling east
so that I may someday serve
the consort of Prince Tolui.
Is that so?
For Princess Sorghaghtani?
[Sitara exhales]
So you're her
lady-in-waiting, eh?
That makes sense,
considering the cleverness
you displayed.
That's kind of you to say.
And well, um...
If I may ask,
how old is the master sage,
exactly?
Hmm.
[CHINQAI] So you wish to know
more about immortality?
Well, my apologies.
Unfortunately, I can't reveal
his secret to you
before the Great Khan learns it.
[SITARA] No. I have no interest
in becoming immortal.
-[CHINQAI] Hm?
-There was a story in a book
that I read when I was younger.
It was about a man who traveled
to India in search of longevity.
But the men he found there
took care of their fathers
and grandfathers
who were too elderly
to even stand.
And also...
My great-grandfather,
I must cover him
with this sheet,
lest the rats nibble
away at him.
But he is still alive,
and that is a blessing.
[SITARA] Upon hearing this,
the man no longer
sought an extended life.
Instead of defying Allah
with immortality,
it is far better to welcome
a healthy and natural death.
That was the moral of the tale.
[Chinqai chuckles]
You know, on second thought,
Master Changchun
did divulge it to me.
-[SITARA] Uh?
-The secret to immortality.
[Sitara breathes uneasily]
You seem like
a very bright girl,
so I'll make an exception
and tell you.
The secret to immortality is...
[Sitara whimpers]
Nonexistent.
We must all welcome
a healthy and natural death.
[SITARA] Uh?
[gasps softly]
Seems sages can be found
in the East and the West.
Our empire may be mighty,
but it's also young.
There are many things
we have yet to learn.
Fatima, such wisdom as yours
is something
our people desperately need.
[SITARA] Uh...
[rain pouring]
[SHIRA] A path to success
based on merit
has opened up to us.
[SITARA] I don't know.
What can someone like me do?
That's why I'm leaving here
on a journey.
[SITARA]
Thinking back to that time,
why did I feel such frustration?
[wind howling]
Keep walking!
We're almost there!
[all breathe heavily]
[soldier sighs]
We made it!
[Sitara pants]
[SITARA] Uh? [gasps]
According to the map
by Al-Biruni I once saw,
I now find myself
at the world's edge.
[wind blows]
[ALL] Cold!
-I can't believe this chill!
-I'm freezing!
[LADY-IN-WAITING] Put these on.
Welcome to
Princess Sorghaghtani's orda.
Her Highness made certain
to supply coats
and warm gers
in preparation for your arrival.
[all gasp]
[indistinct chatter]
Are any of you girls named
Fatima?
[SITARA] Huh?
[LADY] Princess Sorghaghtani.
I've brought the girl.
[SORGHAGHTANI]
You have my thanks...
...for making the long journey
all the way here in this cold.
[Sitara gasps]
How exciting!
You're the one who will be
teaching me this book, yes?
[Sitara gasps]
[♪ closing theme song playing]
[SITARA] Next time, "Otchigin."